Guide to the Democratic Socialists of America Records TAM.105
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series XIII. Subject Files, 1906-2008; 18.17 Linear Feet in 40 manuscript boxes, 1 half manuscript box, and 1 folder in 1 shared box; 7 VHS; 1 Sound_Disc--Vinyl; 3.55 Gigabytes in 60 computer files
  - New York Anti-Sexist Men's Action Network, 1989-1992 (Box 279, Folder 3)
  - Nia Cultural Organization, 1977-1979 (Box 279, Folder 4)
  - Nicaragua, 1979-1995 (Box 279, Folder 5)
  - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA), 1992-2008 (Box 279, Folder 6)
  - Northern California Alliance, 1973-1977 (Box 338, Folder 11)
  - Northern Thunder, 1977-1979 (Box 338, Folder 12)
  - Nuclear Weapons, 1972-1995 (Box 279, Folder 7-8, Box 280, Folder 1)
  - Organizing and Activism, 1974-2004 (Box 280, Folder 2, Box 338, Folder 13)
  - Pacific News Service, 1981 (Box 280, Folder 3)
  - Pan-Africanism, 1999; TW_TAM_105_ER_210
  - Peace and Freedom Party, 1978 (Box 338, Folder 14)
  - Peace Organizations, 1971-2007 (Box 280, Folder 4, Box 338, Folder 15)
  - People for Self-Management, 1974-1975 (Box 280, Folder 5)
  - People's Bicentennial Commission, 1974-1976 (Box 280, Folder 6)
  - People's National Party, 1978 (Box 280, Folder 7)
  - People's Party, 1971-1973 (Box 338, Folder 16)
  - People's Power Players, 1981 (Box 338, Folder 17)
  - Peoples' Alliance, 1977-1979 (Box 338, Folder 18)
  - The Philippines, 1978-1988 (Box 280, Folder 8)
  - Police Brutality, 1978-1998 (Box 280, Folder 9)
  - Political Cases, 1974-1981 (Box 280, Folder 10, Box 281, Folder 1-4, Box 282, Folder 1-3)
  - Political Education Project, 1973-1974 (Box 282, Folder 4)
  - Political Prisoners, 1966-1992 (Box 283, Folder 1-2)
  - Political Rights Defense Fund, 1976-1987 (Box 283, Folder 3)
  - Population Crisis, 1974 (Box 283, Folder 4)
  - Populism, 1983-1988 (Box 283, Folder 5)
  - Prairie Fire Organizing Committee, 1975 (Box 339, Folder 1)
  - Presidential Elections, 1969-1974 (Box 283, Folder 6)
  - Progressive Organizations, 1970-1996 (Box 283, Folder 7)
  - Progressive Political and Citizens' Groups, 1971-1997 (Box 283, Folder 8)
  - Progressive Student Network, 1982-1989 (Box 284, Folder 1)
  - Public Interest Research Groups (PIRGs), 1972-1984 (Box 284, Folder 2)
  - Public Utilities, 1972-1976 (Box 339, Folder 2)
  - Puerto Rico, 1971-1992 (Box 284, Folder 3-4, Box 339, Folder 3)
  - Radical Education Project, circa 1967 (Box 339, Folder 4)
  - Radical Literature Catalogs, 1972-1975 (Box 339, Folder 5)
  - "Radical Women Manifesto", 1973 (Box 339, Folder 6)
  - The Red Umbrella, 1973-1974 (Box 339, Folder 7)
  - The Real World -- Incomplete, 1976-1979 (Box 284, Folder 5)
  - Regionalism, 1972-1980 (Box 284, Folder 6)
  - Religion and Socialism, 1976-1980 (Box 284, Folder 7, Box 339, Folder 8)
  - Religious Groups, 1972-1977 (Box 284, Folder 8)
  - Reproductive Rights, 1970-1980 (Box 339, Folder 9)
  - Republicans, circa 1980-2004 (Box 285, Folder 1)
  - Resist -- Numbers 120, 122-124, 1978 (Box 285, Folder 2)
  - Revolutionary Age, 1966-1975 (Box 339, Folder 10)
  - Revolutionary Socialist League, 1974-1975 (Box 285, Folder 3)
  - Revolutionary Student Brigade, circa 1977 (Box 285, Folder 4)
  - The "Right", 1975-1994 (Box 285, Folder 5)
  - Robert F. Kennedy Memorial, 1968-1975 (Box 285, Folder 6)
  - Rural America, 1979 (Box 285, Folder 7)
  - SANE, National Committee for a Sane Nuclear Policy (Box 285, Folder 8)
  - School for Marxist Education, 1975-1978 (Box 339, Folder 11)
  - Social Democrats, USA/Young Social Democrats, 1967-1981, 1995
    - Paper Files (Box 285, Folder 9-10)
    - Electronic Records, TW_TAM_105_ER_211
  - Social Policy -- Incomplete, 1974-1983 (Box 285, Folder 11)
  - Socialism, Marxism, and Communism -- Publications and Organizations, 1973-1998 (Box 285, Folder 12)
  - Socialism and Communism -- Writings and Comments On, 1973-2005
    - Paper Files (Box 286, Folder 1, Box 339, Folder 12)
    - Electronic Records, TW_TAM_105_ER_212
  - Socialist Feminism, 1972-2005 (Box 286, Folder 2, Box 343, Folder 11)
  - Socialist Labor Party, 1953-1976 (Box 286, Folder 3)
  - Socialist and Labor Songs, 1935-1974 (Box 286, Folder 4)
  - Socialist Liaison Committee, 1978 (Box 339, Folder 13)
  - Socialist Party, USA, 1972-1979 (Box 286, Folder 5, Box 339, Folder 14-15)
  - Socialist Workers Party, 1976-1979 (Box 286, Folder 6, Box 339, Folder 16)
  - South Africa, 1976-1990 (Box 286, Folder 7-8)
  - South America, circa 1977-1981, 1994
    - Paper Files (Box 286, Folder 9)
    - Electronic Records, TW_TAM_105_ER_213
  - Southeast Asia, 1973-1981 (Box 287, Folder 1, Box 339, Folder 17)
  - Spartacist League/Spartacus Youth League, 1973-1977 (Box 287, Folder 2)
  - Speakers' Tours, circa 1985-2000 (Box 287, Folder 3)
  - The Spokeswoman -- Incomplete, 1973-1975 (Box 287, Folder 4)
  - State Democratic Party Platforms, 1978-1980 (Box 287, Folder 5)
  - Student Legal Services, 1976-1977 (Box 287, Folder 6)
  - Student Partisan, Winter 1948 (Box 287, Folder 7)
  - Student Struggle for Soviet Jewry, 1976-1977 (Box 287, Folder 8)
  - Student and Youth Activism and Organizing, 1975-1996 (Box 287, Folder 9)
  - Students for Economic Diversity, 1979-1981 (Box 287, Folder 10)
  - Students for a Libertarian Society, 1980 (Box 287, Folder 11)
  - Sweden, 1979-1984 (Box 287, Folder 12)
  - Synergism, 1972 (Box 340, Folder 1)
  - Tax Reform, 1976-1983 (Box 288, Folder 1)
  - Taxi Rank and File Coalition, 1976 (Box 340, Folder 2)
  - Transfer Campaign, 1977 (Box 340, Folder 3)
  - Trotsky, Leon -- Speeches, 1906-1937 (Box 288, Folder 2)
  - Turkey, 1979-1983 (Box 288, Folder 3)
  - Underground Press Publications, 1982-1987 (Box 288, Folder 4)
  - Unemployment, circa 1972-1979 (Box 288, Folder 5, Box 340, Folder 4)
  - United Auto Workers, 1954-1993 (Box 288, Folder 6, Box 340, Folder 5)
  - United Farm Workers, 1970-1974 (Box 288, Folder 7)
  - United Farm Workers of America -- "Wrath of Grapes" -- Spanish Version, undated (Box 161, Vhs 105.0195)
  - United Mine Workers of America
    - Paper Files, 1973-1979 (Box 289, Folder 1)
    - "They'll Never Keep Us Down: The Story of the United Mine Workers of America Struggle at the Pittston Company", undated (Box 161, Vhs 105.0196)
  - United Nations Association, undated (Box 340, Folder 6)
  - United Peoples Socialist Party, 1974 (Box 340, Folder 7)
  - United States Labor Party, circa 1971-1973 (Box 289, Folder 2)
  - United States Student Association, 1974-2004 (Box 289, Folder 3)
  - United Steelworkers of America, 1974-1985 (Box 289, Folder 4)
  - Unity -- Incomplete, 1979-1988 (Box 289, Folder 5)
  - Universities Committee on the Problems of War and Peace, 1964 (Box 340, Folder 8)
  - Urban Affairs, circa 1945-1983 (Box 289, Folder 6)
  - Vietnam War, 1972-1973 (Box 340, Folder 9)
  - Voting, 1979-2004
    - Paper Files (Box 289, Folder 7, Box 340, Folder 10)
    - Electronic Records, TW_TAM_105_ER_215
  - War Resisters League, 1973-1996 (Box 289, Folder 8, Box 340, Folder 11)
  - "We All Live Downstream" Project, undated (Box 163, Vhs 105.0215)
  - Welfare, 1973-2002
    - Paper Files (Box 289, Folder 9, Box 340, Folder 12)
    - Electronic Records, TW_TAM_105_ER_216
  - Winograd Commission on Presidential Nomination and Party Structure, 1977-1978 (Box 290, Folder 1)
  - Wisconsin Alliance, 1970-1980 (Box 340, Folder 13)
  - The Wisconsin Democrat, July-November 1979 (Box 290, Folder 2)
  - A Woman's Guide to Social Security, 1975 (Box 340, Folder 14)
  - Women and Labor, 1979-1985 (Box 290, Folder 3)
  - Women's Equity Action League, 1973-1974 (Box 290, Folder 4)
  - Women's Organizations, 1976-1994 (Box 290, Folder 5)
  - Workers Defense League, 1972-1983 (Box 290, Folder 6)
  - Workers Party, USA -- Study Outlines and Resolutions, 1938-1944 (Box 290, Folder 7)
  - World Without War Council, 1972-1979 (Box 290, Folder 8)
  - Wounded Knee Bulletin, 1973 (Box 290, Folder 9, Box 340, Folder 15)
  - Young Conservative Foundation, 1985 (Box 290, Folder 10)
  - Young Socialist Alliance, 1974-1976 (Box 291, Folder 1)
  - Young Socialist League, 1954-1955 (Box 291, Folder 2)
  - Youth Communist and Socialist Groups, 1973-1988 (Box 291, Folder 3)
- Series XIV: Archived Websites, October 2007-ongoing; 61 websites in 61 archived websites.
  Scope and Content Note
  This series contains the main website, blogs, and subdomains of the Democratic Socialists of America (DSA), dating back to 2008. http://www.dsausa.org/ contains information on their campaigns and programs, which include student debt alleviation, immigrant rights, environmentalism, Medicare for all, and the protection of social programs, as well as meeting minutes, chapter information, convention materials, fundraising, their scholarship fund, online store, endorsements, videos, and event listings.
  The main DSA website provides links to many of their projects and campaigns, including the Young Democratic Socialists of America, the National Electoral Committee, the Labor Commission, the Anti-War Think Tank, Ecosocialist working group, the International Committee, the DSA Fund, and the Tech Committee. Specific campaign websites were also captured, including Medicare for All, Close the Camps national action (protesting the detention and mistreatment of migrants and refugees, the separation of migrant families, mass deportation, and raids by Immigration and Customs Enforcement), Democratic Socialists campaign for Bernie Sanders, Trans Right and Bodily Autonomy campaign, and a Protect Abortion rights campaign that was launched after the United State Supreme Court overruled Roe v. Wade and limited the right to abortion nationwide. In 2024, the DSA launched a website detailing the organization's goals for the 2024 United States election.
  The series also contains online publications created by the DSA, including Socialist Forum, which intends to facilitate debate and discussion among socialist thinkers and DSA members about ongoing political issues and to develop materials that can be incorporated into future political educational materials; Talking Union blog from the DSA Labor network; Democratic Left, their digital magazine (as well as New American Movement and Moving On, published by NAM); and "Why Socialists Should Become Teachers" digital pamphlet. The online magazine of the Young Democratic Socialists was known as The Activist, which was captured from 2009-2014.
  Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
  Accruals
  New site crawls are accrued semiannually. In 2020-2021, https://workerorganizing.org/, http://www.dsausa.org/, https://y.dsausa.org/, https://democraticleft.dsausa.org/ were accrued monthly.
  Appraisal
  Crawl was limited to domains and subdomains of dsausa.org and docs.google.com/document/ in order to remain within the collection scope and data constraints. Robots.txt (a piece of code designed to limit crawler activity within a website) was ignored.
  Audio for the podcasts have been captured, but might not render in the archived copy. Future changes to the Wayback Machine may allow the files to be played.
  The series is arranged chronologically.
  - Democratic Socialists of America, October 2007-ongoing
  - Young Democratic Socialists of America, November 2008-ongoing
    The website includes chapter information, membership drive materials, how-to guides, caucus organizing, and information on current campaigns.
    Constellation's website, a caucus of the Young Democratic Socialists of America, contains YDSA's principles of expansion, internationalism, party unification, diversity, building labor struggle in campuses, and integration of DSA. It also includes a leadership section, articles written by Constellation members, and an application form to join the caucus.
    Historical Note
    Young Democratic Socialists of America is the youth and student section of the Democratic Socialists of America. Constellation is a caucus of YDSA focused on mass organization.
  - International Committee, July 2009-ongoing
    The website contains quarterly reports, political education resources, statements, and videos from panels and other events with international organizers and political activists.
    The Democratic Socialists of America International Committee works to establish relationships and provide solidarity with socialist and working class organizations internationally. The majority of their work is focused on anti-imperialism and anti-militarism globally, specifically in Cuba, Venezuela, Ukraine, China, Okinawa, Korea, Brazil, Yemen, and United States military bases.
  - The Democratic Socialists of America Fund, October 2013-ongoing
    The related websites host information about the organization's board and history, fundraising materials, as well as educational resources. Additionally, the YouTube channel for the fund contains websites from their educational video series, "How We Win," "We Own the Future: Democratic Socialism--American Style," and "The Big Scary 'S' Word."
    The Socialist Fund is a 501(c)(3) nonprofit organization associated with the Democratic Socialists of America that prioritizes "political education and engagement" in order to increase public awareness of American socialism.
  - Green New Deal Campaign Commission, October 2018-ongoing
    The website highlights their projects, which include Power for Texas, the PRO Act Campaign, the Green New Deal for Public Schools, and the Green New Deal Slate.
    The Ecosocialists Working Group, later the Green New Deal Campaign Commission, of the Democratic Socialists of America seek to help chapters build local power for climate and environmental justice with the backing of a national network; advance an ecosocialist perspective in environmental justice movements, the DSA and greater left; promote understanding of climate science as well as the intersections of capitalism, imperialism, systemic oppression and climate crisis; and build a socialist movement that reflects the needs of the people and planet as an interdependent ecosystem. The working group led the Power for Texas campaign, which was established in response to the Texas power grid failure in February 2021. Other campaigns include the PRO Act (Protect the Right to Organize) campaign, which advocated for the end the "right to work" laws, legalized secondary strikes, and promoted green jobs. The Green New Deal for Public Schools called for the passing of the Green New Deal or Public Schools Act, which includes funding toward green facilities, educators and support staff, comunity engagement, and accessibility. The Green New Deal Slate endorsed local candidates running on the Green New Deal platform. Members of the slate, Hugo Soto-Martinez in California, Elisabeth Epps in Colorado, Rachel Ventura in Illinois, and Sarahana Shrestha in New York were elected in the November 2022 general elections.
  - Religious Socialism, October 2018-ongoing
    The site manages regular blogs and podcasts.
    The Democratic Socialists of America's Religion and Socialism Commission, founded by John Court, seeks to build coalitions between progressive people of different faiths and advance conversations that bridge theology and socialist politics.
  - National Electoral Committee, October 2018-ongoing
    The website contains endorsements, training and support, and endorsement applications.
    The National Electoral Committee is the DSA national body empowered to execute the National Political Committee's political strategy by assisting locals and recommending national endorsements. The NEC includes a national electoral training team and compliance, chapter outreach, endorsement, and training subcommittees.
  - Labor Commission, October 2018-ongoing
    The website contains an organizing guide, organizer training, example workplace campaign petitions and flyers, organizer request form, and a blog. Other projects include the Rank-and-File Strategy, an organizing strategy to bring socialists and organized workers together to build class power, and the Restaurant Organizing Project (ROP).
    The Democratic Socialist Labor Commission is a body of DSA members who are involved in labor unions and labor advocacy movements. The website contains education and training materials for new labor branches and information about the Commission's subcommittees. Subcommittees include the Emergency Workplace Organizing Committee (EWOC), which is a project of the Democratic Socialists of America (DSA) and the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (UE), organized to build a distributed, grassroots organizing program to support workers organizing at the workplace.
  - Medicare for All Committee, October 2018-ongoing
    The Medicare for All website features basic information about the policy proposal, volunteer resources, information about a DSA House pressure campaign, dates for a speaking tour, and a blog that features editorial content about universal healthcare and spotlights DSA chapters' actions related to Medicare for All.
    Democratic Socialists (DSA) for Medicare for All is a policy proposal supported by the Democratic Socialists of America expanding medicare to provide universal federal assistance with costs of medical care for all citizens and abolishing private health insurance.
  - Anti-War Think-Tank, October 2019-October 2020
    The Think-Tank's website features official statements and less formal discussion on such developments as United States' support for Saudi American military presence in Yemen, response to publicized National Security Agency/Department of Defense documents, the civil war in Syria, and other foreign policy developments. The site also solicits submissions from DSA members.
    The Democratic Socialists of America's Anti-War think-tank, established in 2018 and authorized by the DSA National Committee, joined veterans, journalists, and activists to provide socialist commentary on American foreign policy and foreign affairs. The organization sought principled opposition to American Imperialism as crucial to the establishment of socialism in the United States.
  - National Tech Committee, October 2019-ongoing
    The DSA-NTC site features a contact page, forms for volunteers to sign up or request help with technical issues, and a link to an opt-in site.
    The Democratic Socialists of America National Tech Committee is a collection of volunteer tech-workers supporting the technology needs of local chapters and the DSA National Committee.
  - Bread and Roses Caucus, October 2019-ongoing
    The website includes the caucus' platform and action items, and their publication, "The Call." The publication's website contains writing about democratic socialist organizing and administration. The site is also home to a podcast: "The Call Radio."
    The Bread & Roses caucus is a national caucus of Marxist organizers in the Democratic Socialists of America committed to helping build an effective DSA rooted in the multiracial working class.
  - National Political Education Committee, August 2022-ongoing
    The website contains curricula created nationally and by local chapters. Class is a podcast of the National Political Education Committee of the Democratic Socialists of America. The podcast is hosted by Daphna Thier and Elton LK.
    National Political Education Committee was established in 2019 in response to a resolution passed by the National Political Committee of the Democratic Socialists of America. NPEC aimed to help DSA chapters develop the lesson plans, curriculum, and the facilitation skills needed to implement a long-term political education program locally.
  - BDS and Palestine Solidarity Working Group, August 2022-December 2023
    The website contains events and actions, a resource library, an FAQ, a national boycott campaign, and statements regarding their call for Jamaal Bowman's expulsion from the DSA, and other statements surrounding Israeli annexation of Palestine.
    The BDS (Boycott, Divestment, and Sanctions) and Palestine Solidarity Working Group of the Democratic Socialists of America was established in 2019. The working group called for an end to Israel's continued occupation and colonization of historic Palestine; equal rights for Palestinians; and the right of millions of Palestinian refugees to finally return to their home after decades of forced exile.
  - National Conventions, November 2022-ongoing
  - Disability Working Group, July 2023-ongoing
    The linktree webpage provides links to the working group's points of unity, bylaws, code of conduct, national convention resolutions, and other external links on disability justice. DSA Organizing for Pandemic Justice is a resolution proposed by the DSA Disability Working Group at the 2023 National Convention of the Democratic Socialists of America. The website contains the full text of the resolution, chapter safety protocol, a convention COVID-19 safety guide, educational materials, cost analysis, and a timeline of the status of the proposal.
    The Disability Working Group of the Democratic Socialists of America, initially established at the 2017 National Convention, was formed to work toward "inclusion of disabled people in all aspects of DSA and all settings where DSA participates." In response to the COVID-19 pandemic, the working group advocated for events, including the National Convention, to be held in a hybrid virtual and in-person format.
  - Mutual Aid Working Group, December 2023-ongoing
    The website contains information on their projects, the Brake Light Clinics and disaster relief.
    The Mutual Aid Working Group of the Democratic Socialists of America work to provide support to local chapters and provide training on mutual aid.
  - Housing Justice Commission, December 2023-ongoing
    The website contains information on their Emergency Tenant Organizing Committee (ETOC) program, the aim of which is to train tenant organizers and assist in the creation of tenant unions.
    The Housing Justice Commission (HJC) of the Democratic Socialists of America coordinate national and regional campaigns for tenants' rights and support local chapters in the creation and expansion of tenant organizing programs and tenants unions.
  - Trans Rights and Bodily Autonomy Campaign Commission, August 2024-ongoing
    The website contains links to a Trans Sanctuary City Toolkit document, a campaign for Trans Day of Visibility on March 31, and a form to register to Trans Rights & Bodily Autonomy's campaign commission.